<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sick souls salue. By William Sclater. Batchelar of Diuinity and minister of the word of God at Pitmister in Somerset</title>
            <author>Sclater, William, 1575-1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11604</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21845</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116861</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852076</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852076</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17379</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11604)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17379)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 859:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sick souls salue. By William Sclater. Batchelar of Diuinity and minister of the word of God at Pitmister in Somerset</title>
                  <author>Sclater, William, 1575-1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A sermon.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The sicke soules salue.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17379:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17379:1"/>
            <p>THE SICK SOVLS SALVE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> WILLIAM SCLATER.</p>
            <p>BATCHELAR OF DIVINITY <hi>and Miniſter of the word of God at</hi> PIT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MISTER <hi>in Somerſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               <head>AC: OX</head>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed by Ioſeph Barnes. 1612.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17379:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17379:2"/>
            <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>IOHN HORNER</hi> ESQVIRE, and to the devout ANNA his wife, at MELLES in <hi>Somerſet,</hi> mercy <hi>and peace be multiplied.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orſhipfull, If to any thing<note n="a" place="margin">Iſa. 50.4.</note> 
               <hi>the tongue of the Learned</hi> be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in a miniſter, it is to the <hi>mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring of comfort to the weary ſoule.</hi> To moſt other parts of our fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, knowledge ſpeculatiue in a ſort ſufficeth. To this and the appertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, only ſenſible experience. And he ſhall in vaine temper with a wounded ſpirit, that cannot ſubſcribe himſelfe <hi>a</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Apoc. 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>Brother and copartner in the ſame tribulation.</hi> The wiles of <hi>Satan</hi> in this kind, none knowes, but by experience; nor prevents or defeats, except by<note n="c" place="margin">2. Cor. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>the ſame comforts, wherewith himſelfe hath beene comforted of God.</hi> If I ſaid alſo, experience only makes fit h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arers, I ſhould not erre. How God hath dealt with my poore ſoule, either in the wound, or cure, I had rather thankfully acknowledge to my gratious God, then fooliſhly publiſh to inexpert men. This on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I ſay: God is wroth, when he hardens; iuſt, when he breakes; gracious and rich in mercy when he binds vp the ſinners
<pb facs="tcp:17379:3"/> heart. The<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 8.15.</note> 
               <hi>ſpirit of adoption,</hi> is ioyfull: the ſpirit of feare, dreadfull: but the<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 10.8.</note> ſpirit of ſlumber, moſt wofull. They are dead that feele nothing; in the way to life, that feele wrath; they liue indeed, that feele Gods loue in their hearts, infuſed, or inſtilled by the holy Ghoſt. I had rather feele wrath, then feele nothing. But Lord how ſhould they loue thee: whom thou haſt brought from ſecuritie, to feare; from feare, to feeling &amp; experience of thy favour? But I forget the meaſure of an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle. You haue here what you haue felt; the intolerable miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of a wounded ſpirit. Balme alſo from Gilead, if not to cure, yet to aſſwage the griefe. I pray God the Father of mercies, and God of all conſolation, make it ſoveraigne to your ſouls: that as you haue felt the wound, which who can beare? ſo you may taſt<note n="f" place="margin">Phil. 4.7.</note> the peace, that paſſeth all vnderſtanding. Lord Ieſus ſay Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours Worſhips in the neereſt bond. VVILLIAM SCLATER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17379:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PRO. 18.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>A wounded ſpirit who tan beare?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this verſe <hi>Salomon</hi> ſetteth out vnto vs the <hi>ſummum malum,</hi> as I may terme it, the miſerie of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, that can in this life fall into the ſenſe of man. A miſery, which who ſo feeles in extremity, hee would, I dare ſay, excha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge it with the extreameſt of tortures, that mans cruelty can deviſe to inflict.</p>
            <p>A wounded ſpirit. And he amplifies it in a compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of vnlikes. <hi>Protaſis;</hi> the ſpirit of a man will ſuſtaine his infirmity; that is, all other miſeries conſcience paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied can ſolace, and ſuſtaine. <hi>Apodoſis:</hi> But a wounded ſpirit, is an evill intollerable; <hi>who can beare it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſpirit of a man; that is, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, ſetled in peace thorough feeling of Gods loue, <hi>will ſuſtained.</hi> affords ſolace, and ſupport to all other afflictions. Its ſaide of Gods people, they endured<note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 10.34.</note> with ioy the ſpoyling of their goods, <hi>viz.</hi> having conſcience aſſuring them of Gods favour, and promiſed recompence; of the <hi>Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabees,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 11.37.</note> they were ſtoned hewen a ſunder, ſlaine with the ſword, <hi>baniſhed,</hi> famiſhed, and yet endured. Our home Martyrs with what chearefulnes bare they the violence of fire? So mighty a ſupporter of mans weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is a pacified conſcience.</p>
            <p>But a wounded ſpirit, that is, Conſcience it ſelfe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed; when that that ſhould ſolace all other afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is it ſelfe diſcomforted: that hell who can beare?
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17379:4"/> that is to ſay, none without ſpeciall, and even extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary grace ſuſtaining. Of it conſider we two things. 1. The nature of it; what a wounded ſpirit is. 2. The at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute here given it; Intolerablenes; <hi>Who can beare it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A wounded ſpirit, is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience diſtreſſed thorough feare, or feeling of Gods wrath due for ſin. The wound is diſtreſſe; the ſword, Gods wrath: piercing, ſometimes by feare, more then feeling; ſometimes by feeling, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wound is bleeding. The degrees of it are three. 1. That which is called<note n="c" place="margin">Act. 2.37.</note> Compunction, or the pricking of the heart; in compariſon but as the pricke of a pin to the gaſh of a ſword: a lighter diſtreſſe, if any of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may be light, according as the Lord is pleaſed to reſpect our infirmity. And with this, it may be, ſome en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into Gods kingdome. A ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d degree, is that which is here called, the wounded ſpirit; when conſcience is plunged into a deeper diſtreſſe, thorough more fearful apprehenſion of the terrors of the Almighty.</p>
            <p>The laſt degree, is that which the Pſalmiſt cals, the<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 51.17.</note> 
               <hi>Contrite, or broken heart.</hi> A heart as it were ground to powder with the weight of Gods wrath preſſing it. And theſe different meaſures might be all exemplified in Gods children, if daily experience did not evidence them the ſame man feeles ſometimes leſſe, ſometimes more, remorſe being not alwaies in like meaſure in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</p>
            <p>From which different degrees of this wound, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing may be inferred by way of reproofe of ſundry of Gods children. As ſome yee ſhall finde of Gods childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that thinke this their miſery, that they can in no greater meaſure feele the burthen of Gods wrath, due for ſin,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17379:4"/> in their Conſcience. Now if this were their griefe, that they can in no greater meaſure grieue for their ſinnes: ſuch griefe I ſhould cheriſh: But whiles they wiſh for a greater wound, then the Phiſition thinks expedient for their ſtrength, I ſay as our Saviour to the ſonnes of <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedee;</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 20.22.</note> 
               <hi>they know not what they aske.</hi> For can yee drink of the cup? &amp;c. Canſt thou beare the burthen of thy ſins? This wound intolerable, as <hi>Salomon</hi> thinketh it, art thou able to endure? We are not ignorant of<note n="f" place="margin">2. Cor. 2.11.</note> 
               <hi>Satans Wiles;</hi> &amp; we haue great cauſe to feare, if the Lorde ſhould far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preſſe vs, leaſt we ſhould be ſwallowed vp of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. <hi>Luther</hi> ſpeakes excellently to this purpoſe; God many times keepes from his ſervants the horrible, and gaſtly aſpect of their ſins, in wonderfull mercy; leaſt the horror of them, and Gods wrath due for them, ſhould overwhelme vs. And this remember, if you endure the leaſt pricke of this ſword, it is meerely from grace, not from any ſtrength that is in Nature.</p>
            <p>An other ſort there are, &amp; they as heavily complaine of the depth of their wound; as the Church in <hi>Ieremie,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Lam. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>See if there be any griefe like mine, wherewith the Lorde hath afflicted me in the day of his wrath:</hi> was ever any ſo far plunged in diſtreſſe? And here often begin almoſt to quarrell with God himſelfe, and murmur at his hand vpon them, that when he leaues other miſcreants in vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſenſleſnes of their ſpirituall eſtate, he thus heavilie preſſeth, and only not oppreſſeth them. To whom let this adviſe ſuffice. 1. Let them conſider that the cauſe of their wound is in and from themſelues;<note n="h" place="margin">Gen. 3.8.10.11.</note> their ſins pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured it; God only as a iuſt iudge inflicts it. 2. Let them weigh withall, that not only extremity, but even eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17379:5"/> of this horror they haue deſerved; even that which I ſay, hath<note n="i" place="margin">Iſai. 66 24.</note> 
               <hi>the worme that never dieth, &amp; the fire that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver goes out.</hi> And thinke they much, if the Lord for a mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t chaſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he may for ever haue mercy? 3. Tell me thou that murmureſt; whither thinkeſt thou rather to be choſen? A conſcience wounded, or a conſcience ſeared; a hart ground to powder, or a heart paſt feeling of ſin, or wrath? Certainely, though it be true that <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſpeaks, a wounded ſpirit is an evill intolerable; yet if thou haſt any rectitude of iudgement, thou wilt eaſilie acknowledge, the ſtate of a man wounded, farre better, then the ſtate of one hardned; in theſe reſpects at leaſt:<note n="k" place="margin">Act. 16.30.</note> 1 That ſenſe of the wound driues to ſeeke remedie.</p>
            <p>Yea 2<note n="l" place="margin">Iſai. 61.1.</note> prepares, &amp; makes fit to be cured. 4. Let ſuch remember what the Lord ſpeakes to the Apoſtle,<note n="m" place="margin">2. Cor. 12.9</note> 
               <hi>his grace is ſufficient, and he perfects his power in our weaknes,</hi> and hath promiſed,<note n="n" place="margin">1. Cor. 10, 23.</note> 
               <hi>not to ſuffer his to be tempted aboue ſtrength, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, let it not be forgotten, that vſually comforts are<note n="o" place="margin">2. Cor. 1.5.</note> proportioned to afflictions: the leſſe the wounde, the leſſe the comfort; the more the trouble, the more plentifull the conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when God is pleaſed to grant it. And of the nature of this wounded ſpirit, thus farre. Whereto I will adde one thing of ſome conſequence, before I proceed to the attribute, that is, touching the ſubiect, or perſons into whom it is incident; And thus propound the queſtion:</p>
            <p>Whither this miſery may fall into Gods children; or whither it be peculiar only to the veſſels of wrath? To this the anſwere is, that not only caſtawaies or men vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconciled to God, but even veſſels of election, yea the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17379:5"/> deareſt of Gods Saints actually partakers of adoption, are ſubiect vnto it. Yea more, All Gods children, except theſe only in whom the Lord workes extraordinarily, as Infants, &amp;c. ſooner or later, in one meaſure, or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are thus wounded.</p>
            <p>Gods children therefore conſider in a double time, 1. In the act of their calling. 2 After their effectuall vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>In the act of their calling, when God is bringing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the power of darkneſſe, it is generally true of al, they feele it or elſe are never truly called. And this is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, not only by inſtance, but by generall doctrine. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihu</hi> deſcribing the Lords proceedings with his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their firſt converſion, thus ſets it out,<note n="p" place="margin">Iob. 33.14.16.17.18.19.20.21.</note> 
               <hi>God ſpeakes once and twice, and men heare it not, &amp;c. Then opens hee the eares by his corrections which he hath ſealed, &amp;c.</hi> by this eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially here mentioned, as appeares by effects thereof deſcribed in the proceſſe of that Text. Our Savior pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth<note n="q" place="margin">Mat. 9.12.13.</note> he <hi>heales not the whole; but the ſicke; came not to call the righteous, but ſinners,</hi> that is that feele their ſinnes and grone vnder the burthen of them, to repentance. And therefore this once I dare avow; none ever had conſcience truly pacified, that firſt felt not conſcience wounded.</p>
            <p>Now whether a man, after he is in ſtate of grace, may feele this wound bleed a freſh: is a greater queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ſome thorough their weakneſſe; though if we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult with Scripture, and experience, the queſtion is out of queſtion.<note n="r" place="margin">Iob. 33.29.</note> 
               <hi>All theſe things</hi> (ſaith <hi>Elihu</hi> truly) <hi>will God, worke twiſe, or thriſe with a man, that he may turne backe his ſoule from the pit.</hi> Examples are frequent; ſee <hi>David</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:17379:6"/> complaining that hee had<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſ. 32.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>no reſt in his bones by reaſon of his ſinne, his moiſture and marrow conſumed</hi> with the extremitie of this anguiſh.</p>
            <p>Compare Pſ. 77. Iob. 13. that place eſpecially is emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent. 2. Cor. 12. <hi>there was giuen me</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>a pricke to the fleſh, &amp;c.</hi> many interpret it of concupiſcence and the ſtirrings of luſt; but impertinently, and againſt the circumſtances of the place: for ſtirrings of luſt are no gifts of God; neither are in any reſpect to be recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned amongſt infirmities, which <hi>Paule</hi> would reioice in: rather vnderſtand it of this ſting of conſcience which he felt, preſſing him downe to the nethermoſt hell in his ſenſe, that was erſt taken vp to the higheſt heaven.</p>
            <p>If any demand reaſons why the Lord is pleaſed thus to deale with his children, theſe may be aſſigned, whiles we ſet downe the diverſe kinds of this wound, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as the ends of inflicting are diverſe. The kindes are fiue. 1. Penall, inflicted for puniſhment properly ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; ſuch was that of<note n="t" place="margin">Gen. 4.13, 14 Mat. 27.4.5.</note> 
               <hi>Cain,</hi> and <hi>Iudas,</hi> meerely penall, &amp; a beginning of their hell, wherevnto caſtawaies many enter even in this life. 2. Caſtigatory; for chaſtiſement of ſome particular diſobedience; ſuch<note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 32.</note> that of <hi>David,</hi> a chaſtiſement for his ſinnes; the like of many of Gods children: ſo long as they hold on their courſe of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence without interruption, ſo long<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 6.16.</note> 
               <hi>mercy is vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and peace, as vpon the Iſraell of God;</hi> but if once they ſhal turne their liberty into licenſe, when once that peace of God ceaſeth<note n="x" place="margin">Philip. 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>to keepe their hearts</hi> within the bounds of obedience, farewell then their peace till repentance be renued;<note n="y" place="margin">Iob. 13 26.</note> 
               <hi>God then writes bitter things againſt them;</hi> and makes them poſſeſſe the ſinnes even of youth. 3. Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17379:6"/> for triall; ſuch probably was that of <hi>Iob,</hi> chiefly for triall; and ſuch perhaps is that of Gods children ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times moſt ſtrict in obedience. 4. For prevention of ſome future ſin; ſo <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">2. Cor. 12 7.</note> 
               <hi>Leaſt I ſhould bee exalted aboue meaſure.</hi> God in mercy before hand letting vs feele the ſmart, that he may affright from practiſe of ſinne. Saith <hi>Bernard, Quando<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ei, qui peccato quovis obligatus tenetur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern. de tripl. miſericord.</note> 
               <hi>piè immittit Dominus amaritudines quaſdam, quae mente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> occupant hominis, &amp; expellunt pernicioſam delectationem peccati.</hi> God often in his loue, ſeeing vs intangled in ſome ſinne, caſts into our ſoules ſome bitterneſſe to poſſeſſe the minde, and to expel the pernicious delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeneſſe of ſinne. The laſt is of mixt nature; partly for chaſtiſement, partly for triall, partly for prevention. And of one of theſe foure kinds is the diſtreſſe that any of Gods children feele.</p>
            <p>If any would knowe how to put difference betwixt this wound as it is felt of Gods children, &amp; that which is meerely Penall in aliens; let him conſider, the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent effects, or conſequents thereof according as the perſons differ.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Thus workes it vpon Gods ſervants in the firſt fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of it: glad they are to adviſe with any that is able, or likely to afford them comfort; and reſolue what ever the preſcription be, to giue way to it in their practiſe;<note n="a" place="margin">Luk. 3.12, 14.</note> 
               <hi>what ſhall we doe, ſay ſouldiers,</hi> people all affrighted with <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſts thundring ſermon?<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 2.37.</note> 
               <hi>what muſt we do to be ſaved,</hi> ſay the diſtreſſed Iewes, &amp;c? as if they had ſaid, preſcribe what thou wilt, be it never ſo harſh to fleſh and blood, never ſo croſſing to profit, pleaſure, reputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, any thing; we are reſolved to do it, that we may obtaine comfort,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17379:7"/> that a caſtaway ever comes to ſo peremptory, or ſteddy reſolution thou ſhalt hardly finde.</p>
            <p n="2">2 To a child of God,<note n="c" place="margin">Iob 33.23.24</note> 
               <hi>the Interpreter, that one of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand that declares to a man</hi> thus perplexed <hi>Gods righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse,</hi> wilbe for ever welcome,<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 10.15</note> 
               <hi>his feet beautifull that brings the tidings of peace,</hi> &amp; reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cilement with God. Is it thus with an alien, longer then he hath vſe of a miniſter?</p>
            <p n="3">3 The wound once felt makes for ever feareful to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend; Gods childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> once ſcortcht with the flame of Gods wrath, for ever<note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 12. vlt.</note> 
               <hi>dread that conſuming fire;</hi> from others, whiles they are vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the rack, we may hear ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e good ſpee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches; ſeldome ſee performa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is removed.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Such yee ſhall ſee wonderfull<note n="f" place="margin">Mat 5.3.7.</note> compaſſionate to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards others in like miſerie, what they haue felt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not but commiſerate, &amp; pitie in others by experience of ſorrowes they learne compaſſion.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Such, yee ſhall ſee, of all others men of ſtricteſt pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe; and thoſe little ſinnes (as ſome tearme them) which others ſwallow without ſcruple, they carefully fly from, as odious in the ſight of God. More might bee annexed; but this ſhall ſuffice for explaning the nature of this evil; <hi>A wounded ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The attribute followes, which is intolerablenes. <hi>Who can beare it;</hi> that is to ſay, none without ſpeciall, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary grace ſuſtaining. The intolerablenes of this evil I meane not at large to amplifie; hearts, that feele it, eaſily acknowledge it, and I am loath to multiply their feares; thoſe that never felt it, till they feele, will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue. Only take taske; 1 by the fearefull extremities it hath driven many into,<note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 27.5.</note> 
               <hi>Iudas</hi> was not alone in his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable end, but hath had (alas for pitty) and hath
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17379:7"/> daily many followers?<note n="h" place="margin">Iob. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>skin for skin, &amp; all that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath he wil giue for life,</hi> but life yea if it were te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thouſand liues, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that feel this wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in extremity with out hope of re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leaſe, wil prodigally caſt away to be rid of this torture.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The feares it affrights withall are ſtrange<note n="i" place="margin">Prov. 28.1.</note> 
               <hi>They flie,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon, when none purſueth;</hi> even<note n="k" place="margin">Levit. 26.37</note> at <hi>the noiſe of a leafe ſhaken,</hi> tremble at their owne ſhadow; yea are<note n="l" place="margin">Ier 20 4.</note> a terror to themſelues. Affraid (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) and affrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,<note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 53.5.</note> where no feare is.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Yea what extremities hath it brought Gods deare Saints vnto? <hi>Iob,</hi> the mirrour of patience, yet vnder this croſs ſo impatie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſo vnlike himſelf, that<note n="n" place="margin">Iob 6.8.9.</note> he wiſheth for death.<note n="o" place="margin">Pſ. 77.8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>David,</hi> the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after Gods own hart, it draue, if not to blaſphemy, yet to ſome thing neer of kin to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy. The like or greater might be inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced of others.</p>
            <p>Heathens to expreſſe the horrour of it, ſet it out in that fiction of helliſh furies following the flagitious, with burning firebrands, and torturing with all extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. It may perhaps ſeeme ſtrange, this evill ſhoulde be ſo intollerable: paines of the body many by fortitude haue outborne; yea paines of fire, ſome, not only Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs; but miſcreants haue endured; other griefes of the minde, time, or counſell, or neceſſity, or ſomething di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſts. What ſhould be in this point of conſcience to make the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo intolerable? <hi>Reſpon.</hi> There are in this evill two things eminent, more then in other. Firſt, whereas in all other afflictions, man hath to doe with man, or at worſt with Devils; in this man co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>flicteth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly with God himſelfe, fraile man with the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, ſinfull man with the holy God,<note n="p" place="margin">Hab. 1.13.</note> 
               <hi>whoſe eies are pure, and can endure no vncleane thing</hi> to ſtand before
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17379:8"/> him; that is in his wrath<note n="q" place="margin">Heb. 12.29.</note> 
               <hi>a conſuming fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Whereas in all other evils a man is ſtill a friend to himſelfe: in this he is at warre with himſelfe, a ſcourge to himſelfe,<note n="r" place="margin">Ier. 20 4.</note> 
               <hi>a terrour to himſelfe.</hi> And whatſoever he is, or hath, all conſpire to work his torture; vnderſtanding, memory, ſenſes, members, whatſoever is within him, with out him; what he thinks of, remembers, ſees, hears, all turnes to his torment: and therefore no marvell if it be ſo intolerable.</p>
            <p>To draw now to concluſion of theſe generals; thus applying, &amp; making vſe of this attribute of intolerable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes given to this evill. We haue a company of gallants in the world, men for the preſent, as <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeakes,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Eph. 4 19.</note> 
               <hi>paſt feeling, and given over to worke wickednes even with gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe;</hi> that laugh at the ſheepiſhnes of Gods children, who of ſcruple abſtaine from idle, yea from profane ſpeech, yea from lewdeſt and moſt vngracious actions, oathes, periury, whoredome, ſo do my, bloud, any thing alike to them; heaven, and hell, God, and Devill, peace, and trouble of conſcience, all are with them but fables. They talke of <hi>Hell</hi> (ſay they) and torments thereof, as preachers will haue them intolerable; <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Mar. 9.43, 44</note> 
               <hi>worme never dies, and the fire never goes out.</hi> Now if this be al their hel, the gnawing of a worme, &amp;c. who would be ſo fooliſh, as for it to barre himſelfe of the pleaſures of this life?</p>
            <p>Now Lord, that thou wert pleaſed to gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſuch Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts, but one houres ſenſe of that worme which they ſo much ſcoffe at: I am perſwaded its neither poverty, nor priſon, nor ſword, nor fire, nor any other torture, but they would chooſe to make excha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge for it; al the world ſaid one once, for a good conſcience; wonder we at the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17379:8"/> wiſh? The wound of conſcience (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) who can beare?</p>
            <p>Let vs all therefore be admoniſhed to take heed how we wound conſcience, and bring on our ſelues this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable evill. Of all bleſſings of God incident to this life, pray for this, the peace of a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience;<note n="u" place="margin">Phil. 4 7.</note> 
               <hi>it paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paule) all vnderſtanding:</hi> of all miſchiefes, keepe thy ſelfe from this, a torturing, and accuſing conſcience; ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi> who can beare it? Wouldeſt thou knowe what makes it? It is ſinne, any ſinne, be it but a ſcruple, or dram, never ſo little it frets like poiſon in the bowels. It may be indeed, cuſtome of ſinning, as a <hi>callum,</hi> or braw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny skin, makes conſcience ſenſleſſe for the time: but, that <hi>callum</hi> once removed, no fleſh ſo tender. But eſpecially beware of ſinnes againſt Conſcience; that is ſins againſt knowledge, a and recoyled againſt by conſcience: theſe are the torturing ſins indeed, that racke conſcience, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God is pleaſed to awake it: when men<note n="*" place="margin">Iac. 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>know they do evil,</hi> and perhaps heare the voice of conſcience, as another <hi>Lot</hi> admoniſhing,<note n="x" place="margin">Gen. 19.7.</note> 
               <hi>oh deale not ſo wickedly;</hi> or as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to his Miſtris,<note n="y" place="margin">Gen. 39.9.</note> 
               <hi>how canſt thou do this great wickednes and ſin againſt God?</hi> and yet breake out to enormities: theſe feare; they turne in their iſſue, into gall and wormewood. And herein, alas, how deſperat are many? running to practiſe of the groſſeſt enormities, which nature it ſelfe conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ns; as whoredome, drunkennes, &amp;c: and never conſidering (conſcience being thorough cuſtome of ſinning ſtupifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) how deadly they wound it, and what horror they lay vp for themſelues, againſt when God ſhalbe pleaſed to enter iudgement with them. Oh that they would but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table ends of ſuch ſinners, that this<note n="z" place="margin">Gen. 4.7.</note> Lyon
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17379:9"/> of an evill conſcience once rowſed, thorough horrour, driues many vnto. How many (alas) how many every day heare we of running with <hi>Iudas</hi> to the halter, to be their owne hangmen, or cut throats, and poſting as it were, out of the hell of an evill conſcience, to the hel of fire, &amp; brimſtone, burning for ever before the throne of God? And why ſhould any living in the ſame ſins, ſecure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from like iudgement? But of the wound this farre?</p>
            <p n="3">3 Let vs ſee now what that balme is, ſo ſoveraign, that hath vertue to cure it: or in plainer tearmes, what courſe is to be holden of ſuch as are diſtreſſed, that they may finde comfort. Two principall Ingredients wee haue in <hi>S. Peters</hi> preſcript to his patients at <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Act 2.38.</note> 
               <hi>Amende your liues, &amp; 2 be baptized for remiſsion of ſinnes:</hi> ſalues ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne indeed for a wounded ſoule, we can finde none better then repentance 2 and faith, and whatſoever is a meanes to aſſure vs that our ſinnes for Chriſts ſake are forgiven vs. This do therefore, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lords hand ſhall in this kind be vpon thee: ſearch thy heart diligently for whatſoever is amiſſe in thee; leaue neither ſinnes of age, no nor of youth, ſinnes of life nor of nature vnſifted: for all theſe humble thy ſelfe vnder Godes mightie hande,<note n="b" place="margin">Iſ. 1.16, 17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>ceaſe to doe evill, learne to doe well; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> though thy ſins be red as ſcarlet, the Lord ſhall make them white as wooll.</hi> But this be aſſured, never to haue this wound ſoundly cured, till thy ſinnes, thoſe eſpecially thou feeleſt moſt galling, be repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p n="2">2 This done; goe on in thy preſcript, vſing all holy meanes to obtaine faith in the blood of Chriſt;<note n="c" place="margin">Heb 9.14: Rom. 5.1.</note> that blood, and it only, infuſed hath vertue to cure the blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding wounds of conſcience. The meaning is; thou muſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17379:9"/> labour to ſee, and beleeue thine owne ſhare in Chriſts death, and ſatisfaction, that thou maiſt be able to ſay as <hi>Paul</hi> from ſound experience,<note n="d" place="margin">Gal. 2.20.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt loved me, and gaue himſelfe for me.</hi> This perſwaſion once vpon ſound evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence obtained; whatſoever Devill, or conſcience can ſuggeſt for diſcomfort, is eaſily removed; and till that aſſurance in ſome meaſure be gotten, never looke for ſolid peace in thy conſcience. And therefore (by the way) heare not them that teach, you can never be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of your ſalvation, or pardon of ſinnes in this life; what<note n="e" place="margin">Iob. 16.2.</note> 
               <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeakes of his friends in his affliction, is true of ſuch teachers; <hi>miſerable comforters are they</hi> to diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed conſciences. No racke is ſo torturing to the body, as is their doubtfull ſuſpenſe to a wounded conſcience.</p>
            <p n="3">3 And as a meanes to obtaine it, carefully<note n="f" place="margin">Heb. 10 25</note> frequent the aſſemblies and gatherings together of the Saints; where God hath appointed his interpreters, thoſe ones amongſt thouſands, to declare vnto man his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: though it may be, ſome little eaſe may bee obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by other privat helpes, yet ſure they forſake their owne mercy <hi>that forſake our aſſemblies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hetherto ioine Chriſtian prudence, in fitting thy meditations to thy preſent eſtate. The law is indeed a good<note n="g" place="margin">Iac. 1.23.</note> 
               <hi>looking glaſſe,</hi> wherein we may behold the many blemiſhes, and ouglie deformities of our life, &amp; nature; an excellent<note n="h" place="margin">Ier. 23.29.</note> 
               <hi>hammer to breake the ſtone</hi> of the heart: but conſider, the heart broken needs rather<note n="i" place="margin">Iſai. 61, 1.</note> binding, then breaking; the ſpirit wounded, rather lenitiues then co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſiues. In this caſe therefore, Repentance &amp; faith once in any meaſure obtained, that comfort of the Apoſtle is fitteſt to be meditated;<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 6.14.</note> 
               <hi>we are not vnder the law, but
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17379:10"/> vnder grace:</hi> he meanes in reſpect of iuſtification. And therefore though the law condemne thee for remainds of ſinne: yet grace acquits and accepts thee for thy faith in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Laſtly beware of helliſh courſes, which many take; as merry company &amp; ſports, to driue away qualmes of conſcience, as ſome profanely tearme them: the<note n="l" place="margin">Dan. 5.4, 5, 6</note> 
               <hi>hand writing on the wall makes Belſhazzar tremble in midſt of his iollitie:</hi> they are but as a draught of cold water in a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, mitigating the fervour for the preſent, yet ſo as it after exaſperateth the griefe.</p>
            <p>Having thus handled the generals; it remaines now that we proceed to ſome particulars: the rather, for that the weakneſſe of moſt is ſuch in this miſery, that except their owne particular (and the particulars are almoſt infinit) bee ſalued, little, or no eaſe is brought to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed. Our order ſhall be this; Firſt conſider we the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall occaſions out of which this diſtreſſe ariſeth. 2 (For that my purpoſe is to ſpeake of it only as it is in Gods children, for chaſtiſement, or prevention) ſee wee what theſe ſpeciall ſinnes are, which by the ſeverall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes God would correct, or prevent in his ſervants. Laſtly, as the Lord ſhal enable, proceed we to remedies ſuch as either Scriptures, or experience hath approved for ſoveraigne.</p>
            <p>Let no man require exact method, or curious ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them to their heads; no nor enumeration of all particulars, which are almoſt infinite. It ſhall ſuffice to propound thoſe only that occaſioned this paines, and that in the ſame order, which the ſicke ſoule, for whoſe ſake this paines was firſt vndertaken, confuſedly kept in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17379:10"/> vttering her diſtreſſes.</p>
            <p>And in the forefront, place we that that ariſeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuppoſed vnpardonablenes of ſinne. This is the general that moſt affrights; opinion that the Lord either can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not or will not pardon tranſgreſſions committed: ſo long as, but that principle of the Leper is holden,<note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 8.2.</note> 
               <hi>Lord if thou wilt thou canſt make me cleane,</hi> anguiſh of heart is never ſo great.</p>
            <p>The ſinne the Lord would by this diſtreſſe chaſten, or prevent in his children, ſeemes probably this. A for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer conceit they haue had in the daies of their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, that of all things pardon of ſinnes is eaſieſt obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at the hands of God; a ſtroke on the breaſt, &amp; I cry God mercy, thou haſt thought perhaps ſufficient to purchaſe a pardon.</p>
            <p>The Lord would now teach thee, it coſt more to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme a ſoule, and that pardon purchaſed with the price of his own ſonnes blood, is not ſo prodigally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed.</p>
            <p>Now this firſt diſtreſſe is vſually ſtrengthned by three other particulars. 1. Greatneſſe of tranſgreſſions. 2. Long continuance in a courſe of ſinning. 3. Our own indiſpoſition to partake forgiueneſſe. For greatneſſe of ſinne we haue<note n="n" place="margin">Gen. 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>Cains</hi> inſtance. And though the iſſue be better in Gods children, then in the brood of <hi>Cain,</hi> yet the diſtreſſe it ſelfe is incident to Gods deareſt ſervants. And herein alas how wittie, and even Rhetoricall are Gods children to aggravate theire infirmities? ſtill they will be finding out ſomewhat, wherein their ſinnes haue exceeded the ſinnes of others, to which the Lord hath granted pardon. It is true, they confeſſe,<note n="o" place="margin">1. Tim. 1.13</note> 
               <hi>Paule a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17379:11"/> blaſpheamer, a perſecutour was receaued to mercy; but what he did be did ignorantly through vnbeleefe:</hi> I againſt my knowledge, and conſcience. Peter ſinned grievouſly<note n="p" place="margin">Mat. 26.75.</note> but <hi>wept bitterly;</hi> my heart is ſo hardned that not one teare can be wrung out for my many ſinnes. <hi>Manaſſes</hi> ſhed much blood, but in <hi>his tribulation,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Par. 33.12.13</note> 
               <hi>he prayed ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly and humbled himſelfe greatly before the Lord God of his Fathers:</hi> I beſides a few cold wiſhes, and a little han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging downe the head after the guiſe of thoſe Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, <hi>Iſa. 58.</hi> find no ſuch thing in my ſelfe. The ſinne which the Lord would hereby chaſten, and prevent, is our former extenuations, and ſleight eſteeme of the offence of God. we were wont to ſay of our ſins as <hi>Lot</hi> of <hi>Zoar,</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Gen. 19.20.</note> 
               <hi>are they not little ones? and our ſoule may liue.</hi> Oathes, ſay profane men (&amp; perhaps we haue ſaid too) what are they but words? and words, but winde? Scof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing and fabling &amp; wanton ſpeech; but merry talke? Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane ſports, honeſt recreations; groſſer enormities, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane frailties. The Lord would now teach thee other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to eſteeme ſins; to weigh them in the ballance of the ſanctuary, not of thine owne fancy: and perhaps the ſins thou formerlie thoughteſt little, are nowe felt as a burthen too heavy for thee to beare.</p>
            <p>The remedies are theſe. Firſt humble thy ſelfe before the great God, whoſe offence thou haſt ſo lightly eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; pray God to forgiue this thought of thy hart, that ever thou haſt thought any ſin little; and reſolue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to make conſcience as well of ſmaller, as of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſins, knowing that thou art<note n="ſ" place="margin">Mat. 12.36.</note> 
               <hi>countable</hi> for the leaſt, even to <hi>an idle word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When thou haſt this done, conſider then the endleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17379:11"/> of Gods mercy in Chriſt Ieſus; view <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Eph 3.18.</note> 
               <hi>height and depth, and length, and breadth,</hi> thoſe immenſe dimenſions of <hi>Gods grace and loue in Chriſt.</hi> Heare the Lord himſelfe deſcribing himſelfe to <hi>Moſes;</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Ex. 34 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord, the Lord, ſtrong, mercifull, and gracious, ſlow to anger, abundant in goodneſse and truth, reſeruing mercy for thouſands, forgiuing iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and ſin, &amp;c.</hi> So many attributes of mercy and grace, ſo few of power and iuſtice, what argue they? but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a greater propenſion to ſhew mercy then to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute iudgement.</p>
            <p>Heare the Apoſtle.<note n="*" place="margin">2. Cor 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>God the father of mercies;</hi> againe, <hi>God which is rich in mercy.</hi> Heare <hi>Iſay,</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Iſai. 55.7.</note> 
               <hi>He is very readie to forgiue;</hi> heare <hi>S. Iames,</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Iac. 5.11.</note> 
               <hi>of much bowels and tender com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And reiect that ſaying of <hi>Cain</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Gen. 4 13.</note> 
               <hi>my ſin is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then can be forgiven: Mentiris Cain,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Auguſtin;</hi> thou lyeſt <hi>Caine;</hi> for greater is Gods mercy then al ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s iniquitie.</p>
            <p>When thou haſt thus dwelt a while vpon meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the endleſſe mercy of God; ſee then the<note n="a" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.18, 19.</note> price paide to expiate not only little, but even greateſt ſins. Is there any thinkeſt thou ſo great, which the<note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 9.14. 1. Ioh. 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>blood of the ſonne of God, a perſon</hi> ſo excellent, cannot expiate?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nimirum Deus meus</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine) ſi aequa lance delicta peccantis hominis &amp; redimentis gratiâ librentur Authoris; non tantum oriens ab occidente, ſed inferior ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur infernus à ſummo Coeli cardine.</hi> Now ſurely my God (ſaith <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi>) if the offences of man ſinning, and the grace of God redeeming be piezed in even bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, the Eaſt hath not ſo far difference fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Weſt, nor the loweſt hell, from the higheſt heaven, &amp;c. Ad vnto theſe, thoſe ſweete promiſes propounded in the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17379:12"/> word of God.<note n="c" place="margin">Iſai. 1.17, 89</note> 
               <hi>Ceaſe to doe evill, learne to do well, &amp;c. Though thy ſins were red as ſcarlet, they ſhalbe white as wooll.</hi> And out of them frame this comfortable &amp; ſound concluſion. <hi>There is no ſinne capable of repentance, but the ſame is alſo capable of pardon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly conſider examples of great ſinners received to mercy,<note n="d" place="margin">2. Par. 33.12 13.</note> 
               <hi>Manaſſeh, Peter,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">1. Tim. 1.13, 16.</note> 
               <hi>Paul, &amp;c.</hi> and know Gods dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings are exemplary, in them the Lord ſheweth what al might expect, that by their example ſhoulde in after times beleeue and repent.</p>
            <p>A ſeconde particular ſtrengthening this diſtreſſe is long continued practiſe of ſin with contempt of grace offered. This is that that more exaſperates the wound, and makes it bleed a freſh. I know (ſaith the diſtreſſed ſoule) Gods mercies are infinite; Chriſts merit, endleſſe: but I haue long dwelt in practiſe of ſin, neglected ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a gracious invitation, foreſlowed repentance; that now I am perſwaded, the iudgement threatned by the Prophet hath ſeized on me;<note n="f" place="margin">Ezec. 24.13.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe the Lord would haue purged me and I was not purged, therefore I ſhall never bee purged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſin the Lord would hereby chaſten and prevent is procraſtination: &amp; thoſe prophane reſolutions; time enough yet; repent when we are old: and thoſe helliſh ſpeeches, <hi>young Saints old Devils; youth muſt haue his ſwinge; and let vs be merry, we can neuer do it younger.</hi> The Lord would by this diſtreſſe teach thee, that, it is<note n="g" place="margin">Lam. 3.27.</note> 
               <hi>good to beare the yoake in youth;</hi> that repentance the ſooner it is performed, the more comfortable; and that grace muſt be accepted when the Lord offers it, not when we ſhalbe at leaſure. And now I dare ſay, thou wiſheſt,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17379:12"/> thou hadſt bin ſooner wiſe for thy ſoule, and even in youth laid the foundation of thine endles comfort.</p>
            <p>For remedy, this doe: firſt bewaile delaies, now ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable in ſenſe; &amp; pray God to pardon, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous neglect of his gracious invitations. And now purpoſe to<note n="h" place="margin">Ephe. 5.16.</note> 
               <hi>redeeme the time,</hi> and<note n="i" place="margin">1. Pet. 4.2.3.</note> 
               <hi>as much time as remaines in the fleſh, conſecrate</hi> wholly to the ſervice of God.</p>
            <p>This done, build thy ſelfe vpon perſwaſion of this truth: that <hi>promiſe of pardon is made without limitation to any time, perſon, or nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of offences, repentance being once performed. Ieruſalem</hi> had long weltered in the blood of the ſaints: yet heare our Saviour;<note n="k" place="margin">Luk. 19.42.</note> 
               <hi>oh if thou hadſt known but in this thy day, the things that belong to thy peace:</hi> that is to ſay, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding all the blood of the Prophets, and cruelty that hath paſſed from father to ſon along ſo many generations, yet now had repentaunce turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the iudgements prepared for thee. And the Lord by his Prophet; <hi>From the daies of your fathers ye haue gone aſtray, yet returne and I will heale your rebellions.</hi> There is<note n="l" place="margin">Epheſ. 3.18.</note> 
               <hi>a length</hi> as well as a breadth of Gods pardoning mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. It is as long as large, to every one in any time ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly repenting.</p>
            <p>A third occaſion of this diſtreſſe is, that ariſeth from our owne indiſpoſition and diſability to performe the conditions of pardon, faith and repentance. This is that that eſpecially woundeth conſcience. The former prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples after ſome pawſe wilbe granted: God can pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and no time paſt for ſuch as ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> repent. But for me, alas I feele nothing but hardnes of hart and ſecurity: nor ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I, as I ſhould, in any meaſure of godly ſorrow, bewaile
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17379:13"/> my fowle ſins ſo long continued. God cannot pardon a ſinner impenitent and vnbeleeving.</p>
            <p>The ſin the Lord would by this diſtreſſe chaſten, is our former prowd opinion of free will, and conceited ability in our ſelues to beleeue and repent at pleaſure. How oft haue thoſe ſpeeches raſhly paſſed from vs, we will repent in old age, or when the Lorde ſummons vs by our laſt ſicknes; as if we had repentance at co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand, &amp; could at our pleaſure performe it. The Lord woulde now teach thee; that it is not in man to convert himſelf, or to turne from his ſins. And that it is as<note n="m" place="margin">Ier. 13 23.</note> 
               <hi>eaſie for a Blackemore to change his skin, or a Leopard his ſpots, as for a ſinner accuſtomed to do evill to learne to do well,</hi> without a ſupernaturall worke of Gods ſpirit turning vs that wee may be turned.</p>
            <p>Remedies. Firſt humble thy ſelfe before God for this proud conceit thou haſt carried of thy ſelfe in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: acknowledge with the Apoſtle, thine owne diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie ſo much as by<note n="n" place="margin">2. Cor. 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>a thought</hi> or deſire to further thine owne ſalvation; And let God be acknowledged the<note n="o" place="margin">Phil 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>worker both of will and worke</hi> in this point of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion.</p>
            <p>When thou haſt thus humbled thy ſelfe vnder Gods mightie hand, pray then with that poore man in the Goſpel.<note n="p" place="margin">Mark. 9.24.</note> 
               <hi>Lord helpe my vnbeleefe;</hi> and with the Church,<note n="q" place="margin">Cant. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>Drawe me that I may run after thee.</hi> Lord, ſay thou, I knowe<note n="r" place="margin">Ier. 10.23.</note> 
               <hi>it is not in man to convert himſelfe,</hi> nor to turne vnto thee:<note n="ſ" place="margin">Lam. 5.21.</note> 
               <hi>Turne thou me o Lord and I ſhall be turned, Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vert thou me and I ſhall be converted.</hi> And after thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,<note n="t" place="margin">Ezec. 36.26.</note> 
               <hi>take out of my bowels that ſame heart of Stone, and giue inſteed thereof, an heart of fleſh,</hi> remorſefull for ſinne,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17379:13"/> and flexible to the obedience of thy holy will.</p>
            <p>When thou haſt thus craved helpe for thy naturall infirmitie, conſider then that theſe very<note n="u" place="margin">Mark. 9.24.</note> 
               <hi>feelings and ſtrivings againſt vnbeleefe are beginnings of faith;</hi> the fee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling, and bewailing of hardneſſe of heart, is the ſeed of godly ſorrow. And remember howe gratiouſly the Lord hath promiſed not to deſpiſe the deſires of the poore: and how he hath taught very<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 8.26. See Neh. 1.11</note> 
               <hi>ſighes &amp; groanes to be acceptable prayers.</hi> And therefore proportionally very griefe for not grieving, to be godly ſorrow; very ſorrow for not beleeving, to be beliefe, at leaſt in Gods mercifull acceptation. And of this firſt maine diſtreſſe and the ſeverall occaſions thereof, thus farre.</p>
            <p>A ſecond ſpeciall diſtreſſe, is that which is occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by ſuſpicion of hypocriſie: herewith are Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren long and often perplexed, that though they haue performed many excellent things ſavouring of grace &amp; faith vnfained, yet this feare they haue in all theſe been but as hypocrits, either for faſhion, or feare, or vaine glory, or hope of temporal benefit, performing al what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they haue done in religion and the ſervice of God.</p>
            <p>The ſinne the Lord would by this diſtreſſe chaſten, is our former contentment with the ſhadowes of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving graces. Time hath beene perhaps, when wee haue thought civill honeſty to be regeneration; God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue vs, ſound repentance; mumbling of Pater noſters, zealous praiers; formalitie in hearing &amp;c the ſumme of religion. The Lord would now teach thee, its not every faith that ſaueth: and it muſt be more then civilitie that brings to heaven; more then formalitie that makes a Chriſtian; more then lip labour that makes a prayer.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:17379:14"/>
            <p>Remedies. Firſt bewaile this errour, and for it hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thy ſelfe before God, conſidering it is<note n="x" place="margin">Mal. 1.8.14</note> 
               <hi>not the blind and the lame,</hi> nor formalitie that ſatisfies that God, that ſtiles himſelfe <hi>a great king and terrible amongſt the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then;</hi> and hath threatned <hi>a curſe to the deceaver that hath in his flocke a male, and vowes a corrupt thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This done; continue diligently to<note n="y" place="margin">2. Cor. 13.5.</note> 
               <hi>try and examine</hi> the graces that God hath beſtowed vpon thee; it is one end perhaps, why the Lord hath permitted thee to this iealouſie of thine own eſtate. But yet where God giues evidence of ſinceritie, ſhut not thine eies, neither dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate from the worke of Gods ſpirit, that by this ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſſe of thine owne eſtate, and ſtriving for ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, would ſeale vp to thy ſoule, that thou art no hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, but an<note n="z" place="margin">Ioh. 1.47.</note> 
               <hi>Iſraelite indeed, one in whome there is no guile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And perhaps in this view of thy ſelfe, thou ſhalt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover graces in thy ſelfe, ſuch as in that manner cannot be in a hypocrite. <hi>Example:</hi> Thou ſhalt never finde a hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite willing to extenuate his good things, or to ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate his ſinnes. Search and ſee whether in things co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, he be not willing to take notice of the leaſt; yea to arrogate more then is due: to leſſen his ſinnes by al poſſible excuſes. See the hypocrite in his colours; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe forſooth he was<note n="a" place="margin">Luk. 18:11.12.</note> 
               <hi>no fornicator, no extortioner,</hi> &amp;c had given a little ſcattering almes, paid tithes &amp;c. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not men only, but the Lord himſelfe muſt take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of him as of a prime ſervant. Now if thou ſhalt aske thine owne heart, it may bee it will tell thee thou art free from theſe and farre leſſe ſinnes, and yet ſeemeſt to thy ſelfe the<note n="b" place="margin">1. Tim. 1.15</note> 
               <hi>chiefe of ſinners.</hi> Thou haſt done theſe &amp;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17379:14"/> farre greater workes of piety and mercy, and yet thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thy ſelfe not worthy to be numbred amongſt the<note n="c" place="margin">Eph. 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>meaneſt of Gods Saints.</hi> Was ever hypocrite thus opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nioned of himſelfe? I dare ſay not one.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Againe, was there ever hypocrite that could loue a child of God, <hi>eo nomine</hi> becauſe he was a child of God? <hi>Iſhmaell</hi> that hypocrite lived in <hi>Abrahams</hi> familie, was circumciſed, and no doubt performed outward confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie in religious exerciſes vſed by his father: but could<note n="d" place="margin">Gal. 4.29.</note> he loue <hi>Iſaac</hi> the ſonne of promiſe? Yet this I doubt not but thou canſt ſay of thy ſelfe<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 15.4.</note> 
               <hi>Thou honoureſt them that feare the Lord;</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 119 63.</note> 
               <hi>delighteſt their company;</hi> cheerefully according to abilitie,<note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 12.13.</note> 
               <hi>diſtributeſt to their neceſsities.</hi> And whileſt thou ſo<note n="h" place="margin">1. Iohn. 3.14</note> 
               <hi>loueſt the brethren,</hi> canſt thou make queſtion, whether thou be <hi>tranſlated from death to life?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Againe, ever readeſt thou of an hypocrite, that could<note n="i" place="margin">Pro. 9 7,8.</note> loue a rebuker, a man reproving his perſonall ſinnes? We read of <hi>Herod</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Mark. 6.20.</note> he <hi>reverenced Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver that he loved him; yea for his plaine rebuke of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt, he often deſired the murther of him: of the<note n="l" place="margin">Act. 7.54.</note> 
               <hi>Iewes,</hi> that with ſome patience and attention they heard S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Stephens</hi> narration; but his reproofe was as gall and wormewood. Now when thou findeſt <hi>Davids</hi> affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in thee, that thou canſt<note n="m" place="margin">Psal. 141 5.</note> 
               <hi>deſire to be reproved, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt it a benefit:</hi> canſt thou doubt whether the Lord hath made thee<note n="n" place="margin">Prov 9.8.</note> wiſe to ſalvation?</p>
            <p n="4">4 Laſtly, canſt thou name the hypocrite, that ever could ſay, his conſcience bearing him witneſſe, that hee was grieved for imperfections of obedience? mourned for this, that he could in no greater meaſure flie from
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17379:15"/> the corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is in the world through luſt? or that<note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 7.23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>counted this his miſery, to bee led capt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue ſometimes to the law of ſinne?</hi> name that hypocrite if thou canſt. And if thou findeſt theſe things in thy ſelfe: wilt thou be ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurious to thy owne ſoule, ſo vnthankfull to Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit dwelling in thee, as to ſay, he hath wrought no more in thee, then he hath in an hypocrite? God forbid.</p>
            <p>But proceede we to other particulars ſtrengthning in many this iealouſly of their ſincerity. They are 1 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of graces formerly felt in more liuelyhood, &amp; grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter efficacie: this is an vſuall, but a fearefull diſtreſſe; cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing many to thinke of all that ever they haue formerly felt, it was nothing but the hypocrits vaniſhing flaſhes. It is true ſaith the wounded ſpirit; I haue felt that true of my ſelfe that <hi>Iob</hi> ſo comfortably profeſſeth,<note n="p" place="margin">Iob 23.12.</note> 
               <hi>I haue preferred the words of the Lords mouth before mine appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted food;</hi> I haue knowne the day, when I could with ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtnes of affection and feeling of wants, haue powred out my ſoule before my God; I could once haue wept for my ſins, &amp;c. but now alas, and with weeping they vtter it, none of all theſe can I feele in my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>The ſinnes the Lord woulde hereby chaſten or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, are, 1. Pride and that ſwelling of the hart with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitednes of our owne eminency aboue others. 2 Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfulnes for our litle or more grace received. 3.<note n="q" place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.19.20.</note> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>continuance of care to cheriſh and increaſe receaved graces by meanes ſanctified: perhaps wee haue growne remiſſe in hearing, praier, meditation, conference, vſe of ſacraments, &amp;c. 4 Running into occaſions of decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as looſe, profane, irreligious company, from ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſuch as feare God, <hi>by</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>whoſe mutuall faith we might haue ſolaced each another.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:17379:15"/>
            <p>Remedies, 1. Bewaile theſe ſins all or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that thou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt probably think to haue bin occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinings. <hi>2.</hi> This done, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider there may be in Gods dea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſt children decay of graces in part &amp; for a time. Of the church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>ſhee had</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Apoc. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>fallen from her firſt loue,</hi> yet ſtil retained eſteeme of a church, even with the Lord Chriſt. Of the <hi>Philippians</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle;<note n="t" place="margin">Phil. 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>your care beginnes to ſpring againe:</hi> belike they had had their winter, that a new ſpring revived. It is true the Lord hath promiſed that<note n="u" place="margin">Mat. 16.18.</note> 
               <hi>hell gates ſhall never prevaile vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to overthrow our faith,</hi> or any other grace accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying ſalvation: but he hath no where promiſed to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually ſenſible exerciſe of any grace. Faith he preſerveth: but continuall exerciſe of faith hath he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to preſerue? Yea we haue inſtances of his Saints that haue fallen to acts of infidelity: in<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 20.2.</note> 
               <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> himſelf, whoſe faith is ſo renowned; in<note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 26.74.</note> 
               <hi>Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> for firmnes of faith ſirnamed<note n="y" place="margin">Ioh. 1.42.</note> 
               <hi>Cephas.</hi> The Lord will haue his graces eb &amp; flow in his ſervants, ſaith <hi>Auguſtine, ne facilitatem in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus aſſecut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> noſtrum putemus eſse quod eius eſt,</hi> leaſt if we had attained facility in all things, we ſhould thinke that our own which is meerly his work. Who of vs all, doth alwaies heare with equal attentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, reverence, cheereful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, &amp;c: or pray with like earneſtnes of deſire, feeling of wants, aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to be heard? Or do any thing at al times ſo as at ſome?</p>
            <p n="4">4 Laſtly; let it be conſidered, that the Lord vſually withdrawes the vſe of ſome particular grace, that ſome other may in greater meaſure ſhew forth it ſelfe in vs. <hi>Ex:</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Pſ 51.12.14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>Ioy and reioicing</hi> in his mercy he withdrawes that he may bring to practiſe of humiliation.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:17379:16"/>
            <p>A ſecond thing ſtrengthening iealouſie of ſinceritie, is the ſmal meaſure of our graces received. The diſtreſſe hence ariſing, I may well call the good diſtreſſe, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable diſcomfort, ſith this brings with it its own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: yea is itſelfe the matter of moſt ſolide: conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Griefe for little obedience, is it not comfortable?<note n="a" place="margin">2. Cor. 7.11.</note> 
               <hi>indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> at our imperfections, is it not a fruit of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance? See it exemplified, <hi>Mar. 9 24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſin the Lord would: hereby chaſten or prevent, is former contentment with our ſmal meaſures, &amp; that <hi>ſufficit</hi> wee ſang to our ſelues in times of proſperity. Perhaps we haue bin thus minded; any meaſure of faith would ſerue turne for comfort in times of greateſt te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: any meaſure of practiſe, ſo we were free from groſſe enormities, would ſuffice to ſalvation. And it may be we haue ſcoffingly thrown of care of ſtrict car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, with that of <hi>Salomon</hi> profanely miſtaken,<note n="b" place="margin">Ec. 7.18.</note> 
               <hi>wee may be iuſt overmuch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For remedy, hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble thy ſelfe for theſe very thoughts, and pray God to pardon neglects of meanes to growe in grace &amp; in the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This done, conſider that grace is rather meaſured by quality then by quantity: obedience more by ſincerity then by muchnes. Its not ſo much inquired how great or little, but how ſincere obedience is: faith, if it be<note n="c" place="margin">1. Tim. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained,</hi> though but as a<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 17, 20.</note> 
               <hi>graine of muſtard ſeed;</hi> obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, though mingled with many weakneſſes, yet if it be<note n="e" place="margin">Rom, 6.17.</note> 
               <hi>harty,</hi> hath promiſe of gracious acceptation. And if thou lackeſt evidence of ſincerity, take this for one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, griefe for thy defects &amp; imperfections. Let that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17379:16"/> alſo be weighed, that ſmal graces may yet be tru whiles they are ſmal; litle faith is faith, as a little fire is fire, hath the nature of fire as well as the greateſt flame. God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth not little things in obedience offered vnto him. In the ſacrifices of the old law, not the price of the gift, but the ability &amp; affection of the offerer was reſpected.</p>
            <p>In this evill thou art not alone, but haſt<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 8.23.</note> all Gods Saints partakers with thee.</p>
            <p>The ſmalleſt beginnings are<note n="g" place="margin">2. Cor. 1.22.</note> 
               <hi>pledges</hi> of greater fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours where is thankfull acceptance, and<note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 25.23.29.</note> conſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vſe of thoſe already receaved, to the glory of the beſtower.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, let it not be forgotten that <hi>Paule</hi> to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe alleadgeth: what we want in our ſelues,<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 8.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> we haue in Chriſt Ieſus, if not performed, yet puniſhed, and to vs pardoned.</p>
            <p>The third ſtrengthener of iealouſie is preſent inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiblenes of Gods graces working in vs: an vſual accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but a great diſcomfort.</p>
            <p>The ſin chaſtened is, either vnthankfulnes for that ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perience we once had of Gods ſpirit working in vs, or that preſumptuous licence wee tooke to our ſelues in ſinning, whiles our evidence ſtaid firme with vs.</p>
            <p n="1">1 For remedie, pray God to pardon vnthankfulneſſe and preſumption.</p>
            <p n="2">2 This done, conſider graces may ſometimes lie hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in vs, yea worke in reſpect of our acknowledgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t inſenſibly. <hi>The</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Luk. 17.20.21.</note> 
               <hi>kingdome of God,</hi> ſaid our Savior, comes not with obſervation; and it is as<note n="l" place="margin">Mark. 4.26, 27.</note> 
               <hi>ſeed that comes vp and groweth we know not how.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 It was <hi>Davids</hi> caſe,<note n="m" place="margin">Pſ. 50.10.</note> 
               <hi>Create in me</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17379:17"/> cleane heart O God.</hi> His heart, no doubt, was even then cleanſed: for doubt we of cleannes, where Gods ſpirit takes vp his dwelling? or make we queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whether hee<note n="n" place="margin">Zech. 12.10.</note> ſanctifie, where he teacheth to pray? yet <hi>Create,</hi> ſaith <hi>David,</hi> ſpeaking <hi>ad ſenſum,</hi> according to that nothing he felt of cleanſing.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Laſtly remember how diverſly the Lord giues evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of his ſpirits preſence in vs. Somtimes a child of God perceiues little difference <hi>in practiſe</hi> betwixt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and very aliens; yet let him view his affections, hee may ſee grace there: ſometimes againe, more may bee ſeene in practiſe, then in the affection: how ever, whilſt in either, thou haſt cauſe of comfort.</p>
            <p>The laſt particular in this kind diſcomforting, is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from purpoſes, and almoſt vowed reſolutions of a ſteddy courſe in obedience.</p>
            <p>The ſinne the Lord would hereby chaſten or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent; is<note n="o" place="margin">Ec 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>preſumptuouſneſſe in vowing</hi> or reſolving, with out ſerious imploring of Gods aſſiſtance to enable, or due acknowledgement of our owne impotency in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance.</p>
            <p>God wil ever be knowne<note n="p" place="margin">Phil. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>ſole worker of will &amp; work,</hi> of purpoſe and execution. The ſin was<note n="q" place="margin">Mat. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Peters,</hi> and the chaſtiſement he taſted.</p>
            <p n="1">1 For remedy, humble thy ſelfe for raſhneſſe in vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and pray God to keepe thine eies open alwaies, to behold thy naturall weakneſſe and mutabilitie.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Next learne ta diſtinguiſh betwixt the generall &amp; particular purpoſe; I meane betwixt purpoſing to cleaue vnto God in performance of all holy duties, &amp; purpoſing in ſuch meaſure to ſerue him. Perhaps in the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17379:17"/> meaſure and particulars purpoſed, there haue beene faulting, but ſtill in all likelyhood the generall purpoſe remaines.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Put difference betwixt falling from purpoſe, &amp; fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from execution of purpoſe in particulars; there is great ods betwixt the two.<note n="r" place="margin">2. Sam. 11.4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> fell from execution of that<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſ. 119.106.</note> ſworne purpoſe to keepe Gods iudgements, yet not from purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The kinds &amp; degrees of falling would be pondred. There is an<note n="t" place="margin">Heb. 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>vniverſall falling from</hi> the general purpoſe; that indeed is diſcomfortable: and there is a fayling in particular performances; whence without wrong to thy ſelfe, and condemning the whole generation of the iuſt, thou canſt not conclude thy no-adoption.</p>
            <p n="5">5 It would be conſidered whether the<note n="u" place="margin">Heb. 10.26.29.</note> 
               <hi>contrary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane purpoſe</hi> haue ſucceeded in thee. A man can never ſay he is wholly fallen from any grace, till hee ſee the contrary ſucceeding in roome thereof.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Laſtly in this kind fell<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Peter,</hi> and yet obtained mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. And as is aforeſaid, Gods dealings are<note n="x" place="margin">1. Tim. 1.16.</note> exemplary. In one he ſhewes what all in like caſe may on like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions expect.</p>
            <p>Let vs goe on to other particulars; and amongſt theſe, as moſt diſcomfortable, offers it ſelfe, that which ariſeth from abundance and fowlenes of evil thoughts, of blaſpemy, atheiſme, luſt, murther, ſelfe deſtroying, &amp;c. Theſe very thoughts and ſuggeſtions are ſuch, as we thinke cannot ſtand with grace.</p>
            <p>The ſinne the Lord would hereby chaſten, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, is our little acquaintance and notice taking of that greatneſſe of corruption that is naturall vnto vs.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17379:18"/> Originall corruption is little knowne of moſt, how far it ſpreads, and what it compriſeth, till effects thereof be ſeene in vs. And for ſinnes ſo monſtrous wee are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally of Hazaels mind;<note n="y" place="margin">2. Reg. 8.13.</note> 
               <hi>Is thy ſervant a dog that I ſhould doe,</hi> yea or once thinke of ſinnes ſo monſtrous?</p>
            <p>Perhaps alſo it is our lacke of compaſſion towardes others, overtaken ſometimes in ſome action of theſe ſinnes. We haue a precept with<note n="z" place="margin">Gal. 6.1:</note> 
               <hi>meekeneſſe to reſtore ſuch as are fallen;</hi> vpon this conſideration that wee <hi>our ſelues may be tempted,</hi> yea overtaken in acts of the fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt particulars. It is our fault to turne compaſſionate reſtoring into bitter invectiues, &amp; heavy aggravations of our brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s fals; which perhaps occaſions the Lord to permit vs to ſuch like extremities. It may bee its our vnthankfulneſſe for our preſervation through grace from the ſinnes we ſee daily committed by others. The fals of our brethren ſhould be as ſo many ſermons of thankfulneſſe to God, by whoſe grace we ſtand, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citements to humiliation, and watchfulneſſe againſt our owne corrupt inclination: would to God it were not too true of vs, that wee aſcribe our freedome from ſinnes ſo foule, even to goodneſſe of nature. The Lord would now teach vs, that our hearts are equally ſinkes of vncleaneſſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The remedies are, Firſt humiliation and prayer for pardon of theſe ſinnes all, or any of them, we can diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in our ſelues.</p>
            <p n="2">2 For comfort, conſider, firſt whether they<note n="a" place="margin">Iac. 1.14.</note> come out of thine owne corrupt heart, or are<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 13, 2.</note> 
               <hi>caſt into thee by Satan.</hi> If they come from Satan immediatly, they are our croſſes not our ſinnes, till we haue embraced them
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17379:18"/> ſome meaſure of allowance or conſent.</p>
            <p n="3">3 It is a comfortable truth taught by the Apoſtle;<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 7.20.</note> that <hi>no more of our ſinnes is imputed, then wee approue.</hi> What thou diſalloweſt and abhorreſt in thy ſelfe, and ſtriveſt againſt, God never imputes to condemnation.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Laſtly weigh what the Lord aimes at in permitting his children to be thus aſſaulted; and thou ſhalt finde it to be thy benefit, rather then diſcomfort. One end is to acquaint vs with the meaſure of our faulty miſery, that<note n="d" place="margin">Rom 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>as ſinne abounds in our acknowledgement, ſo grace may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in the Lords pardon.</hi> Its our errour to thinke our ſelues naturally inclined to no more ſinnes, then wee feele actually and ordinarily ſtirring in our ſelues. 2. He would by this occaſion ſtirre vs vp to<note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 26.41.</note> 
               <hi>watch and pray</hi> againſt every ſin: even ſuch as through ſecret perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our immunitie from them, often get greateſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage againſt vs. We vſually arme our ſelues againſt no more, then what we feele our ſelues actually and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tempted vnto. 3. He would teach vs to magnifie his grace that hath freed vs from the raigne and dominion of theſe ſinnes; the ſeeds whereof we ſee budding in vs.</p>
            <p>The laſt diſtreſſe which I purpoſe to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude withal, being laſt of thoſe that were propounded by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed; is the long delay of reſtitution after vſe of the meanes. We thinke the Lord ſhould preſently grant what we pray for, and not ſo long withhold comfort conſcionably ſought in the meanes ſanctified.</p>
            <p>The ſinne the Lord would hereby chaſten or preve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, is, our neglect to accept grace offered vnto vs. Perhaps its true of vs that is ſpoken of the Church in the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, when the<note n="f" place="margin">Cant. 5.2, 3.</note> Lord hath <hi>beene wet with the dew of the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17379:19"/> night we hate not opened vnto him,</hi> but foreſlowed the time. Is it not iuſt with him, as <hi>David</hi> ſpeakes, to make as though he heard not, and to differ deliverance?</p>
            <p n="1">1 For remedie, firſt bewaile, and pray for pardon of thine vnthankfull neglects.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Conſider then this is no new thing. The Apoſtle in like Extremitie<note n="g" place="margin">2. Cor. 12 8.</note> 
               <hi>beſought the Lord thriſe,</hi> that is, often before he receaved anſwer.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Though God delay, 1. to chaſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neglects, 2 to kindle affection, 3. that graces ſo hardly obtained may be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued according to their worth: yet<note n="h" place="margin">Luc. 18.7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>will hee not alwaies deſpiſe his children that cry day and night vnto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 God heares diverſly; by giving either the bleſſing deſired, or another equivalent; as if not deliverance, yet<note n="i" place="margin">2. Cor. 12.9.</note> 
               <hi>grace ſufficient</hi> to ſupport vs.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Laſtly, comforts when they come, are vſually<note n="k" place="margin">2. Cor. 1.5.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned to the meaſure of tribulation. Much trouble receaues in the end plentifull conſolation.</p>
            <p>A particular ſtrengthning this diſtreſſe, is feare of falling to ſome fearefull extremities. A thing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with <hi>Iob</hi> was ſo much perplexed, that hee prayed for death to prevent it. I will ſubioine his words.<note n="l" place="margin">Iob. 6.8, 9, 10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>Oh that I might haue my deſire, and that God would grant mee the thing I long for: that is, that God would deſtroy me; that he would let his hand goe, and cut me off. Then ſhould I yet haue comfort, though I burne with ſorrow, becauſe I haue not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the words of the holy one.</hi> Seeſt thou not thine owne caſe exemplified?</p>
            <p>The ſinne the Lord would prevent or chaſten here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is, our former feareleſneſſe of ſuch extremities, ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from proud conceit of abilitie to preſerue our
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17379:19"/> ſelues; and that raſh cenſuring and befooling others, whom the Lord hath been pleaſed thus to humble. We haue heard perhaps of blaſphemies &amp;c. which extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of anguiſh hath droven Gods children vnto; wee haue read of others fearefull diſpaires, wherein they haue periſhed; and began to cenſure them of folly or impietie for ſinnes ſo extreame: nowe the Lord woulde teach vs, that how ever we applaud our ſelues in reſpect of our better ſtay of our ſelues, yet the downfal is head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long when the Lord is pleaſed to leaue vs to our ſelues.</p>
            <p n="1">1 For remedy, pray God to pardon theſe ſinnes.</p>
            <p n="2">2 This done, labour to fortefie faith in the gratious promiſes God hath made thee of ſuſtentation and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation. As faith increaſeth, ſo feare abateth; as it ebs, ſo feare flowes. And to this end conſider<note n="m" place="margin">Ioh. 17.15.24.</note> that Chriſt hath prayed for preſervation from all ſeparating ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treames. And God that cannot lie, hath promiſed<note n="n" place="margin">2. Theſ. 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>to preſerue;</hi> at leaſt not vtterly to caſt off: but though they fall,<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 37.24.</note> 
               <hi>yet to put vnder his hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 To feare ſinne as ſinne, is it not a note of adoption and regeneration?</p>
            <p n="4">4 Thou haſt<note n="p" place="margin">1. Ioh. 5 18.</note> a promiſe of preſervation from the ſin vnpardonable; if others prevaile againſt thee, they may wound thee perhaps, but not vnto death. And of theſe wounds of conſcience thus farre. Other particulars ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny might haue beene inſtanced; but theſe ſuffice for the occaſion. If any deſire more, he hath at hand the labors of theſe reverend ſoule-Phiſitians, <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Greenham, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Perkins,</hi> &amp; <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Downham:</hi> men excellently experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced, &amp; conſcionably travelled in this healing part of divinity.</p>
            <p>Only as an Appendix, ſome generall grounds ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17379:20"/> to be knowne againſt the evil day ſhall bee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The teſtimony of the ſpirit of God<note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 8.16.</note> 
               <hi>witneſsing that we are the ſonnes and daughters of God,</hi> is no vocall teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, ſuch as that of the<note n="r" place="margin">Act. 10.4.</note> Angell to <hi>Cornelius;</hi> but firſt thoſe generall teſtimonies Evangelicall,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ioh. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>Hee that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaues Chriſt.</hi> i. <hi>that beleeues in his name, hath this preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue to be the child of God:</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Mark. 16.16.</note> 
               <hi>and hee that beleeues ſhall bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, &amp;c.</hi> are part of this teſtimonie. 2. That ability Gods ſpirit giues vs to beleeue in Chriſt, is the teſtimony fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence we conclude that we are reconciled vnto God.<note n="u" place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.10.</note> 
               <hi>He that beleeues in the ſonne of God, hath this witneſſe in himſelfe;</hi> his very beleeuing is that witneſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Graces of God out of vs, as <hi>Election, Adoption, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, &amp;c.</hi> are beſt<note n="*" place="margin">2. Pet. 1.10. 2. Tim 2.19.</note> diſcerned by graces within vs, as <hi>Faith, Loue, Patience, Obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 In temptation it is<note n="x" place="margin">Pſal 51.12.</note> not ſafe to iudge of our Adop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, and Iuſtification, by peace of conſcience, and ioye in the holy Ghoſt: but rather by our holy affections, &amp; inclinations to obedience; <hi>As feare of God, and care to depart from evill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 In anguiſh of ſoule it's ſafeſt to looke <hi>ad minima;</hi> to the leaſt ſeedes and graines, as I may tearme them, of grace. As<note n="y" place="margin">Neh. 1.11.</note> 
               <hi>deſire to feare God;</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Gal. 5.17.</note> 
               <hi>luſting againſt corruption; griefe for our imperfections; diſlike</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Rom 7.15.</note> 
               <hi>and diſallowance of our ſelues, and our actions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 The g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory of faith ſtands in this<note n="b" place="margin">Pſalm. 22.1. Iob. 13.15.</note> 
               <hi>to beleeue aboue ſenſe,</hi> yea againſt feeling.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Holineſſe makes vs not accepted of God; but<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 2, 5.</note> 
               <hi>ſhew ethonly that we are approved of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 Our ſervices are not approved for the goodnes of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17379:20"/> our performa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; but they are<note n="d" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>acceptable to God through Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8 In the agonie of conſcience none more vnfit to iudge of vs, then our ſelues: though at other times wee are ſicke of ſelfe loue, and too partiall in our own caſe; yet in this ſtate we are moſt vncharitable to our ſelues.</p>
            <p n="9">9 When thou art brought loweſt by affliction,<note n="e" place="margin">Pſ. 32, 3, 4, 5.</note> hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thy ſelfe lower vnder Gods mightie hand, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging his iuſtice in thy affliction, and thine owne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe to receaue the leaſt comfort. There is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret pride in our hearts even when we are brought low<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt by afflictions.</p>
            <p n="10">10 The more vile thou art in thine owne eies, the more pretious art thou in the ſight of God.<note n="f" place="margin">Iſai. 57.15.</note> 
               <hi>Hee dwels with him that is of a contrite and humble ſpirit, to reviue the ſpirit of the humble, and to giue life to them that are of a contrite heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11 Let no ſeeming vnfitneſſe keepe thee from exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes religious publique, or private. The weakeſt perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances are farre more acceptable then whole of omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
            <p n="12">12<note n="g" place="margin">Pſ. 32.1, 2.</note> Remiſſion of ſinnes and peace of conſcience are favours worth waiting for. If the Lord ſhould keepe thee on the racke even till the laſt gaſpe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part the leaſt drop of his ſonnes blood to purge thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, vnſpeakeable were his mercy towards thy ſoul.</p>
            <p n="13">13 Conflicts with corruption are infallible ſignes of grace.</p>
            <p n="14">14 Victorie over Satan ſeemes doubtfull, thorough ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> infirmitie: is<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 16.20.</note> certaine, by the promiſe of God.</p>
            <p n="15">15<note n="i" place="margin">2. Cor. 12.9.</note> 
               <hi>Gods power is perfitted in his childrens weakneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
